"lang" { 
"Language" "dutch" 
"Tokens" 
{
"#commentary\tf2-Comment000.wav"   "[Gabe Newell] Welkom bij Team Fortress 2. We hopen dat het wachten na negen jaar ontwikkeling de moeite waard is geweest. Je kunt naar een toelichting luisteren door het richtmerk op het zwevende commentaarsymbool te plaatsen en de gebruikstoets in te drukken. Je kunt de toelichting stoppen door het richtmerk op het draaiende knooppunt te plaatsen en de gebruikstoets opnieuw in te drukken. Bij sommige toelichtingen wordt de game overgenomen om je iets te laten zien. In deze gevallen druk je gewoon weer op de gebruikstoets om de toelichting te stoppen.  Laat me weten wat je ervan vindt als je er even mee hebt kunnen spelen. Je kunt me bereiken op gaben@valvesoftware.com en mijn favoriet is de spion. Bedankt en veel plezier!"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment000.wav"   "[Gabe Newell] Welcome to Team Fortress 2. After nine years in development, hopefully it will have been worth the wait. To listen to a commentary node, put your crosshair over the floating commentary symbol and press your use key. To stop a commentary node, put your crosshair over the rotating node and press the use key again. Some commentary nodes may take control of the game in order to show something to you. In these cases, simply press your use key again to stop the commentary.  Please let me know what you think after you have had a chance to play. I can be reached at gaben@valvesoftware.com, and my favorite class is the spy. Thanks, and have fun!"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment001.wav"   "[Jeremy Stone] Bij multiplayer games wordt de inhoud die de spelers verwerken voor het grootste deel gegenereerd door andere spelers.  We hebben dit verbeterd door functies toe te voegen die de relaties tussen spelers kunnen verbeteren.  
Door bijvoorbeeld een stilstaand beeld van zijn moordenaar kan de speler zich bepaalde lastige tegenstanders herinneren.  De kwelgeestfunctie is een extra herinnering dat bepaalde vijanden belangrijker zijn dan andere.  Hij maakt een kleine lus voor negatieve bekrachtiging door spelers een mogelijkheid te geven extra punten te scoren door iemand uit wraak te doden.
"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment001.wav"   "[Jeremy Stone] In multiplayer games, the content players consume is largely generated by other players.  To enhance this, we added features designed to promote relationships between players.  
For example, the freeze-cam shot of a player's killer helps the player remember specific, troublesome opponents.  The nemesis feature adds an additional reminder that certain enemies are more significant than others.  It creates a small negative reinforcement loop by giving players an opportunity to score extra points with a revenge kill.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment002.wav"   "[Laura Dubuk] Voor kaarten zijn onoverschrijdbare grenzen nodig, maar tenzij we de omgevingen beperken tot binnenruimtes of steile ravijnen kunnen deze grenzen het zicht van de speler op het omliggende, onbereikbare terrein niet altijd verhinderen. In onze wat meer realistische titels, zoals HL2, zijn voor deze grenzen vaak fictieve en visuele verklaringen nodig. In de zwaar gestileerde wereld van Team Fortress is opvallende kunstmatigheid echter een belangrijk ontwerpprincipe. We kunnen deze verklaringen zodoende vereenvoudigen of gewoon weglaten zonder dat de ervaring van de speler eronder lijdt. Bij het testspelen werd bijvoorbeeld duidelijk dat deze lage hekken die naar een lege vlakte leiden de boodschap overbrachten dat het gebied achter het hek niet interessant en verboden terrein is."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment002.wav"   "[Laura Dubuk] Maps require impassable boundaries, but unless we restrict the environments to either interior spaces or steep canyons, these boundaries can't always block the player's view of the outlying, unreachable area. In our more realistic titles, like HL2, these boundaries often require fictional and visual explanations. In the heavily stylized Team Fortress world, however, conspicuous artificiality is a core design principle and so we can simplify or altogether ignore these explanations without compromising the player experience. Playtesting showed, for instance, that these low fences leading to an empty expanse successfully conveyed the message that the area beyond the fence is uninteresting and out-of-bounds."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment003.wav"   "[Ariel Diaz] Elke klasse van Team Fortress is ontworpen om een unieke bijdrage te leveren aan aanval en verdediging, en controleposten zijn eigenlijk manieren om de aandacht van de speler te vestigen op deze belangrijke aanvals- en verdedigingsactiviteiten. Ze zijn ook handig om spelers naar bepaalde punten op de kaart te lokken."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment003.wav"   "[Ariel Diaz] Each of the Team Fortress classes was designed to make a unique contribution to attack and defense, and control points are, fundamentally, methods of focusing players' attention on these core offensive and defensive activities. They're also useful for drawing players to different points of the map."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment004.wav"   "[Jeff Lane] Bij het oorspronkelijke ontwerp verloren de aanvallers alle vooruitgang die ze bij het veroveren van de post hadden geboekt als ze eenmaal bij een controlepost waren verslagen. Bij het testspelen bleek dat een enkele speler in de buurt van een vijandelijke controlepost geen enkele stimulans had om die post in te nemen als er vijanden in de buurt waren. Als een team bovendien nog maar een enkele controlepost te verdedigen had, slaagde het sterkere, aanvallende team er vaak niet in de laatste post gedurende de volledige veroveringsperiode aan te vallen, waardoor te veel games eindigden in een patstelling. We hebben het veroveringsmechanisme veranderd zodat de verovering een tijdje behouden blijft nadat de aanvallers van de controlepost zijn verdreven. Met deze verbetering zijn beide problemen met het oorspronkelijke ontwerp opgelost.
"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment004.wav"   "[Jeff Lane] In our original design, once attackers were cleared off a point, they lost any progress they'd made toward capturing the point. Playtests revealed that lone players near an enemy control point had no incentive to try to capture it if any enemies were in the area. Furthermore, once a team was reduced to defending a single control point, the stronger attacking team was often unable to successfully assault the final point for the full capture period, which caused too many games to end in a stalemate. We changed the capture mechanic so that capture progress persists for a while even after the attackers are cleared off the point, and this improvement fixed both of the problems with the original design.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment005.wav"   "[Jim Hughes] Als je spelers interessante navigatiemogelijkheden wilt geven, moeten de routes door een kaart variëren in effectiviteit naar gelang de huidige klasse van de speler en de status van de kaart. Door water wordt het nemen van een bepaalde route kostbaarder omdat zwemmen langzamer gaat dan rennen. Spionnen nemen dat vaak voor lief, om ongemerkt te kunnen infiltreren. Pyro's vermijden dat omdat hun belangrijkste wapen onder water waardeloos is. Als de vijand een sterke verdediging heeft, wordt de extra moeilijkheid van de waterroute het overwegen waard voor klassen die de verdedigers in de rug willen aanvallen."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment005.wav"   "[Jim Hughes] To give players interesting navigation decisions, routes through a map should vary in effectiveness based on the player's current class and the state of the map. Water lets us increase the cost of taking a particular route, because swimming is slower than running. Spies often accept that cost in order to infiltrate undetected. Pyros avoid it because their primary weapon is useless underwater. If the enemy has a strong defense, the increased cost of the water route becomes a worthwhile tradeoff for any class trying to hit the defenders from behind."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment006.wav"   "[Iikka Keranen] We bouwen onze 3D-skyboxen op schaal 1/16 om het geheugen dat voor de grote ruimtes daarin wordt gebruikt te beperken. Dit betekent dat het een precisiewerkje wordt bij de treinen die tussen de skybox en de spelersruimte rijden. Er zijn eigenlijk twee versies van elke bewegende trein: eentje op de schaal van de speler voor de werkelijke spelruimte, en een heel kleine in de skybox. De kleine reparatiewerkplaatsen aan beide kanten van het middelste gebouw verbergen het punt waar we de twee treinen wisselen."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment006.wav"   "[Iikka Keranen] We build our 3d skyboxes at 1/16th scale to reduce the memory used by the large spaces in them. This means we have to get a little tricky when dealing with trains moving between the skybox and the player space. There are actually two versions of each moving train; A player-scaled one for the actual gameplay space, and a tiny one out in the skybox. The small repair sheds on either side of the middle building disguise the point at which we swap between the two trains."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment007.wav"   "[Andrea Wicklund] In het meest ideale geval moet een wedstrijd eindigen in een overwinning voor een team en een verlies voor het andere. Patstellingen betekenen in feite een verlies voor beide teams. In ons kaartontwerp wordt rekening gehouden met twee belangrijke variabelen om patstellingen te voorkomen: de tijd die een team nodig heeft om te respawnen en de reistijd van het punt waar men respawnt tot aan de frontlinie. Het winnende team krijgt wat snellere tijden om te respawnen en meer voorwaartse punten, een lus voor positieve bekrachtiging waardoor het een grotere kans krijgt om door te stoten en de game te winnen."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment007.wav"   "[Andrea Wicklund] Ideally, matches should end in a victory for one team and a loss for the other. Stalemates are essentially a loss for both teams. To avoid stalemates, our map design considers two key variables: team respawn times and travel time from the respawn point to the frontline. The team that's winning gets slightly faster respawn times and more forward respawn points, a positive reinforcement loop that increases the chances for them to push forward and win the game."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment008.wav"   "[Dave RIller] Om sluipschutters te kunnen herbergen, moeten kaarten grote open vlaktes, lange zichtlijnen en beschermende dekking bieden.  De doelwitten van de Sniper moeten alternatieve routes hebben om de zichtlijnen van de Sniper te kunnen omzeilen, hoewel deze vaak kostbaar zijn omdat ze bijvoorbeeld extra tijd kosten.  De spelers hebben hier dus een keuze: nemen ze de rechtstreekse maar gevaarlijke route of de veiligere maar langzamere route?  Sluipschutterposities hebben gewoonlijk ook een overeenkomstige vijandelijke sluipschutterpositie aan de andere kant van de arena, waardoor een sluipschutter in de tegenaanval kan gaan tegen de andere en teamgenoten dekking kan bieden in open gebieden."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment008.wav"   "[Dave RIller] To accommodate snipers, maps need wide open spaces, long sightlines, and protective cover.  Targets of the Sniper require alternate routes that bypass the Sniper's sightlines, though these usually have an additional cost, such as increased travel time.  This leaves players with a choice:  do they take the more direct, but hazardous route, or the safer yet slower route?  Sniper positions generally also have a corresponding enemy sniper deck, positioned on the other side of the arena, which allows one sniper to counter another, offering cover for teammates in exposed areas."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment009.wav"   "[Bay Raitt] Patstellingen ontstaan doorgaans rond deuren waar de teams aan beide kanten van de opening een sterke verdediging hebben. Om dit te omzeilen hebben we alternatieve routes met hoge reiskosten toegevoegd zodat het alleen aantrekkelijker wordt als de vijand een sterke verdediging op de hoofdroute heeft. Het aantal vijandelijke toegangspunten tot een gebied is van cruciaal belang voor het ontwerp omdat het ontzettend moeilijk is om een gebied te behouden als de vijand van meerdere kanten nadert. Daarom zijn eenrichtingsuitgangen handige ontwerptools omdat we daarmee het aantal vijandelijke toegangspunten kunnen loskoppelen van het aantal eigen aanvalsroutes."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment009.wav"   "[Bay Raitt] Stalemates generally occur around doors, where teams have a strong defensive presence on either side of the opening. To help counter this, we provide alternate routes with high travel costs that become more attractive only when the enemy has strong defenses behind the main route. The number of enemy entry points into an area is crucial to its design, since it's extremely hard to hold an area when enemies approach from multiple fronts. This makes one way exits a useful design tool, since they let us uncouple the number of enemy entry points from the number of friendly offensive routes."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment010.wav"   "[Jamaal Bradley] Voor de gameplay moeten we de snelheden van de klassen soms neutraliseren. Deze timers op de deuren van het centrale gebied zijn bijvoorbeeld gemaakt om ervoor te zorgen dat alle klassen het kunnen halen tot het middelste gedeelte van de kaart tegen de tijd dat de actie werkelijk losbarst. Bij het testspelen werd duidelijk dat het eigenlijk veel leuker was om de teams als groep te laten wachten zodra de deuren open gaan. Het afwachten van het gevecht in combinatie met de gevaarlijke bewegende treinen zorgt voor een groot begingevecht om de middelste controlepost."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment010.wav"   "[Jamaal Bradley] For gameplay purposes, we sometimes need to neutralize the speeds of the classes. For instance, these central door timers were created to ensure that all classes could make it to the middle part of the map by the time the action actually starts. Playtesting showed that it was more fun to have the teams waiting as a group as soon as the doors open. The anticipation of battle, combined with the hazardous moving trains, creates a great opening clash for the middle control point."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment011.wav"   "[Matt Boone] Kogelvrij glas is een handig trucje bij zwaar verdedigde gebieden, bijvoorbeeld bij controleposten. Het biedt het aanvallende team de mogelijkheid om de vijandelijke verdediging en sentrygun-posities te bekijken, terwijl het verdedigende team de zich verzamelende aanvallers goed in de gaten kunnen houden. Dit is vaak cruciaal voor de verdediging als de aanvallers wachten op een onkwetsbaarheidslading van een Medic."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment011.wav"   "[Matt Boone] Bulletproof glass is a useful design tool in strongly defended areas, such as around control points. It gives the offensive team a chance to see enemy defenders and sentrygun positions, while affording the defensive team a good view of the gathering attackers. This is often crucial for the defense if the offense is waiting for a Medic's invulnerability charge."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment012.wav"   "[Matthew Russell] Op aanvals-/verdedigingskaarten is bij patstellingen meestal een aanvallend team in een zwakke positie betrokken dat met het hoofd tegen de muur loopt terwijl de timer afloopt. Om dit te vermijden, raden we aan vermoedelijke verliezen zo snel mogelijk te laten escaleren tot werkelijke verliezen. We beginnen met een korte tijdslimiet en voegen dan tijd toe wanneer het aanvallende team erin slaagt een controlepost in te nemen. Op deze manier wordt de ronde in een zo kort mogelijke tijd uitgespeeld en blijft het voortdurend spannend. Lange rondetijden dragen niet bij aan het idee van urgentie dat we proberen te creëren."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment012.wav"   "[Matthew Russell] On Attack/Defend maps, stalemates generally involve a weakly positioned attacking team beating its head against the wall as the timer bleeds out. To avoid this, we encourage likely losses to snowball into actual losses as quickly as possible. We start with a short time limit, and then add time whenever the offensive team succeeds in capturing a point. This way the round plays out in as short a time as possible and keeps the tension high throughout. Long round times aren't conducive to the sense of urgency we want to create."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment013.wav"   "[John Cook] Hoogte is een handig element bij het ontwerpen van verdedigbare gebouwen. Het gebouw Cap B moet bijvoorbeeld van alle kanten worden verdedigd. De hoogte en de ramen aan alle kanten bieden de verdedigers in dit gebouw een voordeel wanneer ze van binnenuit raketten en granaten afvuren. Dankzij kogelvrij glas in een aantal ramen kunnen ze naderende vijanden veilig bekijken."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment013.wav"   "[John Cook] Height is a useful feature when designing defensible buildings. For instance, the Cap B building needs to be defended from all directions. The height, and windows on all sides, give defenders in this building an advantage, when launching rockets & grenades from within. Bulletproof glass in some windows lets them safely view approaching enemies."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment014.wav"   "[Jake Nicholson] Voor Soldiers ontwerpen we ruimtes waarbij we speciale aandacht besteden aan de hoogte. Soldiers schieten gewoonlijk het liefst van boven af op de tegenstander om het effect van de raketschade te maximaliseren. Het dak biedt ze dat voordeel. Dit kan ook worden bereikt met de raketsprong van de Soldier waardoor deze meestal onbereikbaar is voor andere klassen. Vanwege de schade die wordt veroorzaakt door een raketsprong moeten Soldiers medkits inruilen voor het hoogtevoordeel. Door deze ruil en het gebrek aan medkits op het dak, wordt het dak een effectief voordeel zonder de kaart uit balans te brengen, omdat de Soldiers zullen moeten vertrouwen op de Medics op de grond om ze fit te houden."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment014.wav"   "[Jake Nicholson ] For Soldiers, we design spaces with specific attention to height. Soldiers generally want to be shooting down at opponents to maximize the effect of their rockets' splash damage. The rooftop here gives them that advantage. It can also only be reached with the soldier's rocket jump, making it generally inaccessible to the other classes. Because of the splash damage from a rocket jump, soldiers have to trade health for the height advantage. This tradeoff, coupled with the lack of health on the roof, lets usmake the rooftop a powerful advantage without unbalancing the map, since soldiers will need to rely on medics down below to keep them healthy."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment015.wav"   "[Dave Riller] Voor de Scout-klasse moeten kaarten open ruimtes hebben waardoor Scouts kunnen dubbelspringen langs routes die voor andere klassen onbegaanbaar zijn.  Dit gebied is voorzien van verschillende daken en rotspartijen waarover een Scout zich kan verplaatsen terwijl hij boven eventuele andere tegenstanders blijft.  Scouts profiteren vaak van hun snelheid om terug te trekken en medkits te verzamelen. Hier dwingen we ze dus om een bepaald risico te lopen door de medkits in een kleine, afgesloten ruimte te plaatsen waarvoor ze enige bewegingsvrijheid moeten opgeven."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment015.wav"   "[Dave Riller] To accommodate the scout class, maps need open spaces that allow scouts to double jump along paths that the other classes can't navigate.  This area features a variety of rooftops and rocks that a scout can traverse while staying above any non-scout opponents.  Scouts often use their speed advantage to retreat and collect health, so here we force them to adopt some risk by placing the health inside a small, enclosed area, where they sacrifice some freedom of movement."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment016.wav"   "[Matt Boone] De Spy is ontworpen voor spelers die hun tegenstanders te slim af willen zijn. Op hoog niveau is hij vooral bezig met het infiltreren in vijandelijke teams, verplaatst hij zich in vermomming en valt hij vijanden, meestal Snipers, Engineers en Medics, aan met zijn doodsteek in de rug. Zijn onzichtbaarheidsmantel is gemaakt om hem in twee belangrijke situaties te helpen. Ten eerste bij het passeren van de frontlinie waar spelers het meeste op hun hoede zijn voor vijanden en argwanend zijn als vrienden zich niet in de juiste richting begeven. Ten tweede bij het ontsnappen aan vijanden die zijn vermomming hebben doorzien terwijl hij op vijandelijk terrein is. Met zijn sapper kan hij gemakkelijk onbewaakte, vijandelijke sentryguns uitschakelen, waardoor vijandelijke Engineers worden gedwongen hun gebouwen goed in de gaten te houden."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment016.wav"   "[Matt Boone] The Spy is designed for players who want to outsmart their opponents. At a high level, his gameplay flow is to infiltrate the enemy team, move around while disguised, and use his instant-kill backstab to take out key enemies, usually snipers, engineers, and medics. His invisibility cloak is designed to help him in two key situations. The first is in getting past the frontline, where players are most vigilant against enemies and most suspicious of friends not heading in the right direction. The second is in escaping from enemies who have seen through his disguise while he's in enemy territory. His sapper was designed to allow him to easily take out unattended enemy sentryguns, forcing enemy engineers to keep a close eye on their buildings."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment017.wav"   "[Eric Kirchmer] Het in balans brengen van de kracht van de door kunstmatige intelligentie gestuurde sentrygun van de Engineer was een van de moeilijkere ontwerpproblemen in Team Fortress 2. Als het wapen te krachtig zou zijn, zou het alleen kunnen worden uitgeschakeld door de meest bedreven spelers. Als het wapen te zwak zou zijn, zou de Engineer geen kans hebben tegen ervaren spelers waardoor eigenlijk alle redenen om het überhaupt te bouwen vervallen. Onze oplossing was om van de sentrygun in feite een binair wapen te maken, wat inhoudt dat het dodelijk is voor tegenstanders die geen dekking zoeken, maar niet slim kan omgaan met vijanden die afwisselend dekking gebruiken. De Engineer wordt hierdoor gedwongen om zijn vaardigheden met zijn secundaire wapens in te zetten om de zwakte van de sentrygun bij hoeken te compenseren en de sentrygun tegelijkertijd te gebruiken als angstaanjagend obstakel voor tegenstanders die proberen er langs af te sprinten."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment017.wav"   "[Eric Kirchmer] Balancing the strength of the Engineer's AI-controlled sentrygun was one of more difficult design problems in Team Fortress 2. If the gun was too powerful, only the most skilled players would be able to counteract it. If the gun was too weak, the Engineer would have no chance against skilled players, effectively eliminating any reason to build it in the first place. Our solution was to make the sentrygun essentially binary in the sense that it's lethal to opponents who don't take cover, but can't intelligently deal with enemies popping in and out of cover. This forces the Engineer to use his own secondary weapons skill to compensate for the sentrygun's corner weakness, while still making the sentrygun a formidable obstacle for any opponent simply attempting to sprint past it."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment018.wav"   "[Andrew Burke] De Scout is ontworpen voor spelers die zich snel kunnen verplaatsen terwijl ze hun doelwit volgen. Terwijl andere klassen het moeten hebben van grote schade, vertrouwt de Scout op zijn hoge bewegingssnelheid en mogelijkheid om te dubbelspringen om vijandelijk vuur te ontwijken. Zijn gevechtsstijl is vooral opgebouwd rond de mogelijkheden van zijn primaire wapen, de scattergun. Dat richt een enorme schade aan maar heeft een flinke reikwijdte waardoor hij dicht bij de vijand moet komen voor het volledige effect, maar waar hij ook het grootste risico loopt om te worden geraakt. Het wapen heeft een lage vuursnelheid waardoor hij het vuren onderbreekt, dan wegduikt, dan weer onderbreekt, enzovoort, waardoor vijanden een grotere kans hebben om hem tijdens de intervallen te raken. Bovendien heeft het wapen maar een klein magazijn en een lange herlaadtijd zodat de Scout eerder uit het gevecht zal stappen om te herladen. Dat kan hij met zijn snelheid gemakkelijk doen zodat gewonde vijanden een kans hebben om weg te komen voordat de Scout terugkomt."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment018.wav"   "[Andrew Burke] The Scout is designed for players who are able to rapidly move around while tracking their target. Where other combat classes rely on high amounts of damage, the Scout relies on his high movement speed and double jump ability to dodge enemy fire. Much of his combat style is crafted through the features of his primary weapon, the scattergun. It does a large amount of damage, but has a wide spread that forces him to get close to the enemy for full effect, where he's also at highest risk of being hurt. It has a slow rate of fire that encourages him to pause to fire, then dodge, then pause, and so on, which gives enemies a higher chance to hit him at intervals. Finally, it holds a small clip and a slow reload time to encourage the Scout to pull out of combat to reload, something which he can do easily with his speed, and gives injured enemies a chance to run before the Scout returns."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment019.wav"   "[Dhabih Eng] De Soldier is een klasse basisstrijder met veelzijdige bewegingen en capaciteiten voor schade op lange afstand. Hij is zodanig ontworpen dat hij zich huis voelt in elke gevechtssituatie en is de beste klasse anti-sentrygun lange afstand. De belangrijkste zwakke punten zijn verwerkt in zijn primaire wapen, de raketlanceerder. Het wapen heeft maar een klein magazijn waardoor de Soldier het herladen zorgvuldig moet plannen, en het vuurt relatief langzame projectielen waardoor het buiten een bepaald bereik ongeschikt is tegen tegenstanders die goed kunnen wegduiken, zoals de Scout."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment019.wav"   "[Dhabih Eng] The Soldier is a core combat class featuring versatile movement and terrific long range damage capability. He's designed to be comfortable in almost any combat situation, and to be the best long-range anti-sentrygun class. His main weaknesses are designed into his primary weapon, the rocket launcher. It has a small clip size, which forces the Soldier to carefully manage his reloads, and it fires relatively slow-moving projectiles, making it ineffectual beyond short range against any opponent who dodges well, like the Scout."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment020.wav"   "[Charlie Brown] Het snipergeweer vormde een andere ontwerpuitdaging. Om aan de verwachtingen van de spelers te voldoen, moet een snipergeweer de mogelijkheid bieden een tegenstander met een enkel schot in het hoofd uit te schakelen. Anderzijds moeten we ervoor zorgen dat het niet snel kan vanaf de heup worden afgevuurd omdat het dan, in de handen van een ervaren speler, het dodelijkste korteafstandswapen van de game wordt, waardoor de primaire zwakte van de Sniper teniet wordt gedaan. Dit hebben we opgelost door een oplopende schademeter te implementeren die alleen wordt weergegeven als er wordt ingezoomd op de Sniper. Deze oplossing heeft verschillende gunstige bijeffecten: 
De kleine schade zonder inzoomen en wanneer voor het eerst wordt ingezoomd, zorgt ervoor dat Snipers geen tegenstanders kunnen doden door spontaan een schot te lossen. Door de oplaadtijd kunnen Snipers snel schoten lossen die weinig schade aanrichten of langzaam zeer schadelijke schoten afvuren, waardoor tegenstanders hen in een gecoördineerde aanval kunnen overmeesteren. De grote schade aan het einde van de lading werkt als beloning voor Sniper-achtig gedrag zoals het vinden van een geschikt uitkijkpunt en het lossen van heel doelbewuste schoten.
"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment020.wav"   "[Charlie Brown] The sniper rifle was another tricky design problem. To meet players' expectations, a sniper rifle has to be able to kill an opponent with a single shot to the head. On the flip side, we need to ensure it can't be snap fired from the hip with the same effect, because then, in the hands of an experienced player, it also becomes the game's most lethal short range weapon, negating the Sniper's primary weakness. To solve this, we implemented a charging damage meter that only appears when the sniper is zoomed. This solution has several beneficial side effects: 
The low damage both while un-zoomed and at the initial zoom ensures that Snipers can't kill opponents with impromptu snap fire. The charge time means Snipers can deal out low damage shots quickly or highly damaging shots at slow intervals, which allows opponents to overwhelm them with a coordinated rush. The high damage at the end of the charge rewards Sniper-esque behaviors, such as locating a decent vantage point and taking very deliberate shots.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment021.wav"   "[Marc Scaparro] De Pyro is ontworpen als de beste klasse korteafstandsvechter die spelers moet aanmoedigen om meer met hinderlagen te gaan spelen. We hebben de Pyro hiervoor kwetsbaar gemaakt in open ruimtes, waardoor spelers worden gedwongen om afgesloten ruimtes en ingangen te doorzoeken. We hebben de Pyro op de korte afstand nog dodelijker gemaakt door de effecten van de vlammenwerper zichtbaar lawaaierig te maken. Tegenstanders worden dan lang genoeg gedesoriënteerd om door de vlammen te worden gedood."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment021.wav"   "[Marc Scaparro] The Pyro is designed to be the best short-range combat class, aimed at encouraging players to adopt an ambush style of play. To achieve this, we made the Pyro vulnerable in the open, which forces players to seek out enclosed areas and doorways. To add to the Pyro's short range lethality, we made the flamethrower effects visually noisy, which helps disorient opponents long enough for the flames to finish them off."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment022.wav"   "[Wade Schin] De Demoman is de meest veelzijdige klasse strijder die snel kan wisselen van sterke aanvallen tot een sterke verdediging. Hij is de enige in de game met indirecte vuurcapaciteiten waardoor hij om een hoek sentryguns kan uitschakelen. Bovendien kan hij met zijn kleefbommen hogere sprongen maken, vergelijkbaar met die van de raketsprongen van een Soldier. Met de kleefbommen wordt bovendien voorkomen dat vijanden door ingangen komen, wordt de terugtocht gedekt en worden controleposten zelfs verdedigd als Demoman elders is."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment022.wav"   "[Wade Schin] The Demoman is the most versatile combat class, capable of rapidly switching from strong offensive pushes to defensive area denial. He has the only indirect fire capability in the game, allowing him to take out sentryguns around the corner, and his sticky bombs give him a grenade jumping ability similar to that of the Soldier's rocket jumps. His sticky bombs can also prevent enemies from moving through doorways, cover a retreat, and defend control points even when the Demoman is somewhere else."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment023.wav"   "[Keith Huggins] Met het ruime vuurbereik van de minigun van Heavy kunnen spelers die niet heel snel kunnen richten en schieten zich toch in het strijdgewoel storten. Dit tekort aan schutterscapaciteiten van de speler hebben we gecompenseerd door andere vaardigheden belangrijker te maken. Door de voorbereidingen op het schieten en de lagere snelheid van Heavy tijdens het schieten worden spelers gedwongen zowel het begin van het gevecht als naderende aanvallen door de vijand af te wachten."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment023.wav"   "[Keith Huggins] With its wide field of fire, the Heavy's minigun lets players who don't have great twitch-aiming skills still wade into the thick of combat. To make up for this reduction in the value of the player's aiming skill, we amplified the importance of other skills. For instance, the wind-up time before firing and the heavy's reduced speed while firing force players to learn to anticipate both the start of combat and incoming enemy attacks."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment024.wav"   "[John Morello] De Medic heeft met name een ondersteunende functie. Eerder ontworpen ondersteunende klassen kenden diverse problemen. Er waren niet veel vaardigheden voor nodig omdat ze achterbleven in verdedigde gebieden waardoor ze bovendien uit de leukste gedeeltes van de game werden gehouden. Het ergste was dat dit betekende dat ze niet eens erg nuttig waren omdat ze meestal niet in de buurt waren van de spelers die hoog nodig genezen moesten worden. Met de Medic van Team Fortress 2 zijn deze problemen opgelost, met name door ze voornamelijk in het heetst van de strijd te houden. Bovendien hebben we de Medigun zo eenvoudig mogelijk in gebruik gemaakt zodat Medics zich kunnen concentreren op overleven terwijl ze teamgenoten genezen. Richten is nauwelijks nodig, waardoor Medics zich kunnen concentreren op het volgen van hun genezingsdoel, dat dus voldoende reden heeft om zijn Medic te beschermen."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment024.wav"   "[John Morello] The Medic is the main support class. Previous support classes we've designed had a variety of problems. They didn't require much skill, because they stayed back in defended areas, which also kept them out of the funnest parts of the game. Worst of all, this meant they weren't even terribly useful because they generally weren't near the players who most needed to be healed. We designed the Team Fortress 2 Medic to solve these problems, primarily by focusing on keeping them right in the thick of battle. Additionally, we designed the medigun to be as easy to use as possible, so that Medics can focus on survival while healing teammates. Virtually no aiming is required, which lets Medics concentrate on following their heal target, who has a huge incentive to keep his Medic benefactor safe."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment025.wav"   "[Aaron Halifax] Het belangrijkste doel bij het ontwerpen van de Medigun was het creëren van een sterke relatie tussen de Medic en zijn genezingsdoel.  We wilden zien wat er zou gebeuren als we ons zouden richten op het scheppen van een sterke band tussen twee spelers in plaats van er alleen voor te zorgen dat de rest van het team samenwerkt.  Het ontwerp van de Medigun zorgt ervoor dat de Medic en zijn doel zich zeer bewust zijn van elkaar, elkaars gezondheid en relatieve posities in de gaten houden en zorgvuldig tactische beslissingen nemen.  We wilden dat er vaardigheid nodig zou zijn om een goed genezingsdoel te zijn, zodat de Medics ervaren doelen zouden opzoeken en zich daaraan zouden koppelen.  Dit is bevorderlijk voor de relatie die we zoeken."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment025.wav"   "[Aaron Halifax] Our main goal in designing the Medigun was to build a strong relationship between the Medic and his healing target.  We wanted to see what we would get if we focused on creating a tight loop between two players, instead of just thinking about getting the larger team to cooperate.  The Medigun's design ensures that the Medic and his target are extremely conscious of each other, watching their health and relative positions, and making tactical choices carefully.  We wanted there to be skill involved in being a good healing target, so that Medics would seek out and latch onto skilled targets.  This helps foster the relationship we were after."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment026.wav"   "[Jakob Jungels] Onkwetsbaarheid voegt een snelheidselement toe aan de multiplayer-ervaring die anders minder emotionele hoogte- en dieptepunten kent dan een goed gemaakt spel voor één speler.  Wanneer een onkwetsbare Medic en zijn maatje komen binnenstormen, is dat een enorm hoogtepunt voor ze.  Het is ook spannend voor de verdedigers die weten dat ze gedurende 10 seconden moeten volhouden totdat de onkwetsbaarheid verzwakt.  Onkwetsbaarheid draagt ook bij aan de snelheid door een team te helpen een verdedigingsimpasse te doorbreken wanneer een vijandelijk team in zijn schulp kruipt en weigert de basis te verlaten.  Zonder een gebrek aan verdedigende verkenners is het makkelijker voor de aanvallers om de onkwetsbaarheidslading zonder onderbreking op te bouwen.  Bovendien is onkwetsbaarheid een belangrijke doelstelling voor de Medic en wordt hij beloond omdat hij een goede genezer is. We moedigen het gedrag aan door meer lading toe te voegen wanneer de Medic gewonde teamgenoten geneest dan wanneer hij teamgenoten geneest die bijna helemaal gezond zijn."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment026.wav"   "[Jakob Jungels] Invulnerability adds an element of pacing to the multiplayer experience, which otherwise tends to have fewer emotional highs and lows than a well-crafted single player game.  When an invulnerable Medic & his friend come running in, it's an extreme high point for them.  It's also a rush for the defenders, who know they've just got to hold on for 10 seconds until invulnerability fades.  Invulnerability also sharpens pacing by helping a team push through a defensive stalemate, when the enemy team turtles up and refuses to come out of their base.  Without a lack of defensive skirmishers, it's easier for the offense to build up the invulnerability charge without interruption.  In addition, invulnerability is a great goal for the Medic and rewards him for being an effective healer. We encourage the behavior by adding more charge when the Medic is healing injured teammates than when he's healing ones who are already at full health."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment027.wav"   "[Jeff Lane] Multiplayer-community´s concentreren zich vaak op een klein aantal kaarten en spelen die steeds weer.  In plaats van een groot aantal kaarten te maken waarvan de meeste toch niet zouden worden gespeeld, besloten we te proberen een enkele kaart te bouwen met een grotere natuurlijke herspeelbaarheid dan we ooit hadden gebouwd.  Bij de meeste multiplayer-kaarten weet je al wat je gaat doen voordat de kaart ook maar is geladen.  In ons geval wilden we een kaart waarbij je niet eens zoiets basaals als je beginpunt zou kunnen voorspellen, laat staan wat je zou doen als je daar zou belanden.  Hydro begint daarom met een gerandomiseerde beginstatus.  Doordat de nadruk ligt op het winnen van de controle over voortdurend veranderend terrein voelt de kaart zelden aan als een herhaling.  De duidelijk ronde structuur houdt de teams intussen geconcentreerd en zorgt ervoor dat er de nodige hoogte- en dieptepunten zijn naarmate de teams terrein winnen en verliezen."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment027.wav"   "[Jeff Lane] Multiplayer communities tend to focus on a small group of maps, playing them over and over again.  Instead of producing a large number of maps, most of which would go un-played, we decided to try and build a single map with more innate replayability than any we'd built before.  With most multiplayer maps, you know what you'll be doing before the map has even finished loading.  In our case, we wanted a map where you couldn't predict even something as basic as your starting point, let alone what you would be doing when you got there.  Hydro therefore begins with a randomized starting state.  The emphasis on control of constantly shifting territories means the map rarely feels repetitive.  Meanwhile, the explicit round structure keeps teams focused, and provides regular highs and lows as the teams gain and lose territory."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment028.wav"   "[Kerry Davis] In games worden de stats gewoonlijk weergegeven als een vergelijking van de speler met de rest van de wereld.  Dat is eigenlijk alleen interessant voor de mensen die helemaal aan de top staan.  Bij TF2 hebben we besloten dat het waarschijnlijk beter is om de stats te vergelijken met de eerder behaalde scores van de speler zodat het geen wereldwijd vergelijkingssysteem maar een gepersonaliseerd en motiverend systeem is. De beginnende speler krijgt zo de aanmoediging dat hij steeds beter wordt, ook al is hij nu nog niet zo bedreven. De veteranen krijgen te zien of ze in de buurt van hun vorige record zijn gekomen, waardoor ze worden aangemoedigd dat record te breken.  Het persoonlijke stats-systeem werkt tevens als een validatiesysteem. Als een speler het gevoel heeft dat hij een goede game heeft gespeeld, verschijnt het stats-systeem op het scherm met het bericht 'Inderdaad, dat was een prima game.'"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment028.wav"   "[Kerry Davis] Games usually approach stats by comparing the player to everyone else in the world.  This is only really of interest to those who are near the top.  With TF2 we decided that a better approach might be to compare stats to the player's previous successes, turning them from a worldwide comparative system into a personalized motivational one. The beginning player gets encouragement and acknowledgement that while they're not highly skilled yet, they're getting better all the time. The veterans get to see when they've managed to come close to their previous record, which encourages them beat that record.  The personal stat system also acts as a validation system. When a player feels like they've had a really good run, the stats system pops up and essentially says, 'You're right, that was a great run.'"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment029.wav"   "[Andrea Wicklund] Hoe meer duidelijke visuele voorstellingen er kunnen worden gebruikt, hoe minder werk er nodig is om de game-elementen uit te leggen. De eerste versie van TF2 was enorm gedetailleerd. In de loop van de tijd kwamen we erachter dat dat een hoop problemen veroorzaakte.  Het was moeilijk de verschillen tussen de spelersklassen duidelijk weer te geven.  Wapens die andere zaken dan kogels afvuurden, waren moeilijk te visualiseren.  Onze kaarten zouden niet echt logisch zijn in de echte wereld, waar twee vijandelijke krijgsmachten hun bases zelden bouwen op nog geen vijftien meter afstand van elkaar.  Bovendien was de game niet visueel anders dan onze andere producten.  Een gestileerde wereld had deze problemen niet: zet de massieve Heavy naast de Spy in krijtstreeppak en spelers begrijpen zowel het verschil in het aantal medkits tussen de klassen als de enorm verschillende speelstijlen.  De genezende straal van de Medic was voor de testspelers meteen duidelijk toen ze het zwevende rood en de symbolen het doel in zagen stromen.  Gestileerde fictie kan gemakkelijk uitleggen waarom de bases van de teams zo dicht naast elkaar zijn gebouwd.  Ten slotte is een screenshot van TF2 gemakkelijk te herkennen zodat niemand het kan verwarren met een van onze andere games."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment029.wav"   "[Andrea Wicklund] The more your art direction can use well-understood visual representations, the less work you have to do to explain your game elements. The earliest version of TF2 had a heavily realistic art direction. As time went on, we found this was causing us a lot of issues.  The differences between our player classes were hard to expose satisfactorily.  Weapons firing anything other than bullets were hard to visualize.  Our maps didn't make a lot of sense in the real world, where two opposing forces rarely build bases within fifty feet of one another.  In addition, the game wasn't visually distinct from our other products.  A stylized world had none of these problems:  Put the massive Heavy next to the pinstripe-suited Spy, and players understand both the numerical health differences between the classes and their very different gameplay styles.  The medic's healing beam was easily understood by playtesters when they saw the floating red plus symbols streaming into the target.  A stylized fiction can easily explain why the team's bases are built right next to each other.  Finally, a TF2 screenshot is easily recognizable, ensuring that no one will confuse it with another of our games."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment030.wav"   "[Moby Francke] Nadat we hadden gekozen voor een gestileerde vormgeving, experimenteerden we met verschillende stijlen voordat we kozen voor het voorbeeld van J.C. Leyendecker, een enorm populaire illustrator die rond 1900 leefde. De manier waarop Leyendecker kleding en materiaal weergaf was voor ons een geweldig voorbeeld voor de manier waarop we personages detail konden geven en de heldere, scherpe omtrekken die zo belangrijk waren voor de klasse-indeling konden behouden. Voor het maken van vouwen in kleding gebruikten we normale kaarten die een prima detailniveau vormden wanneer je ze van dichtbij bekijkt, zonder afbreuk te doen aan de kleuren die de aandacht van de speler naar het zo belangrijke wapentuig moeten trekken."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment030.wav"   "[Moby Francke] Having decided on a stylized art direction, we experimented with a variety of styles before settling on the example of J.C. Leyendecker, an enormously popular illustrator of the early 1900s. Leyendecker's rendering of clothing and material provided a great example of how to add detail to a character while keeping the clean, sharp silhouette shapes that were key to our class identification. We used normal maps to craft folds of clothing, which provided a fine level of detail when seen up close, without detracting from color values meant to draw the player's eyes to the all-important weaponry."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment031.wav"   "[Ariel Diaz] De personages zijn de belangrijkste elementen in een multiplayer game, dus daar hebben we de meeste aandacht aan besteed.  We hebben een leeshiërarchie gemaakt voor spelersmodellen, door prioriteiten vast te stellen voor de informatie die spelers moeten kunnen zien door alleen maar naar het model te kijken.  Die hiërarchie is als volgt: ten eerste in welk team ze zitten, ten tweede in welke klasse ze spelen en ten derde welk wapen ze gebruiken.  De teamaanduiding werd verduidelijkt door voor elk team een algemeen kleurschema te gebruiken, waarbij we warme kleuren kozen voor het rode team en koude kleuren voor het blauwe team.  De klasseaanduiding werd verduidelijkt door het silhouet van het personage te gebruiken. De unieke vormen van silhouetten en animaties zijn duidelijker op grotere afstanden en bij meer verschillende lichtniveaus dan andere visuele details van het model. Het wapen werd tenslotte gemarkeerd door de structuren. De gebieden met het meeste contrast, die de aandacht van de speler trekken, concentreren zich allemaal rond de borstkas van de modellen, precies daar waar ze hun wapen houden. Bovendien zorgt de subtiele overgang van het donker rond de voeten naar de lichte gedeelten rond de borstkas van het personage ervoor dat de ogen van de spelers naar de wapens worden getrokken."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment031.wav"   "[Ariel Diaz] Characters are the most important piece of art in a multiplayer game, so that is where we spent most of our effort.  We developed a read hierarchy for player models, prioritizing the information that players needed to be able to read merely by looking at the model.  Our hierarchy was this: first, what team they're on, second, what class they're playing, and third, what weapon they're wielding.  Team readability was addressed by adopting an overall color palette for each team, picking warm colors for Red and cool colors for Blu.  Class readability was addressed through the character's silhouette. Unique silhouette and animation shapes are more identifiable at far distances, and across a broader range of light levels, than any amount of other visual detail on the model. Finally, the weapon was highlighted through the textures. The areas of highest contrast, which attracts player's eyes, are all focused around the chest area of our character models, right where they hold their weapon. In addition, the subtle gradient from darkness around the character's feet, to the bright areas around the chest, also helps draw the player's eyes to the weapons."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment032.wav"   "[Charlie Brown] Spelersklassen zijn de ruggengraat van de gameplay van TF2. Er zijn vele redenen waarom dit zo'n handig ontwerptool is. Een klasse is een verzameling ervaring die uniek moet zijn in vergelijking met de andere klassen in de game. Een speler die op een klasse is uitgekeken, kan overstappen naar een andere klasse en daar nieuwe ervaring opdoen. We kunnen zo tegemoet komen aan spelers met verschillende vaardigheden en wensen. Beginnende en ervaren spelers kunnen zo samen plezier beleven. Of je nu een voorzichtige denker, een strategische verdediger of een zenuwachtig schietende adrenalinejunk bent, er is voor ieder wat wils. De ontwerpbeslissingen die we voor de Team Fortress 2-klassen hebben genomen, betekenen dat we een groot aantal spelersniveaus in de game kunnen hebben terwijl de beslissingen van de enkele speler beheersbaar blijven."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment032.wav"   "[Charlie Brown] Player classes form the backbone of TF2's gameplay. There are a bunch of reasons why they're a useful design tool. A class is a bottled up experience, designed to be unique relative to the other classes in the game. A player who is getting tired of one class can switch to another class and get a fresh experience. They allow us to cater to players with a variety of different skills and desires. Beginning and advanced players can have fun together. Cautious cerebral thinkers, strategic defenders, and twitch firing adrenaline junkies can all find their niche. Team Fortress 2's Class design decisions enable us to have a larger number of player abilities in the game, while still keeping a single player's decisions down to a manageable level."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment033.wav"   "[Robin Walker] We hebben TF2 voor het eerst gepresenteerd op de E3 in 1999, en nu is het alweer 2007. Waarom heeft het dus zo lang geduurd?  Het korte antwoord is dat het zo lang duurde om iets te maken waar we tevreden over waren.  Voor het lange antwoord moeten we het ontwikkelingsproces eens bekijken.  Kern van de zaak is de veronderstelling dat we van tevoren niet echt weten wat leuk is.  We weten wat leuk was in het verleden.  Maar als op tafel drie ideeën liggen, kunnen we niet echt zeggen welke het leukste zal zijn.  Dus hebben we ons geconcentreerd op het ontwikkelen van een herhaalbaar proces waarmee we daar achter kunnen komen.  Het is gebaseerd op een cyclus van voortdurende herhaling, waarbij de evaluatie wordt gedaan door zo veel mogelijk mensen de game te zien spelen.  Bij het ontwikkelen van TF2 hebben we heel veel dingen uitgeprobeerd. Een aantal daarvan zijn in het eindproduct verwerkt, maar de meeste zijn weggelaten.  In de eerste versies van TF2 probeerden we bijvoorbeeld een game op te bouwen rond het idee van een commandant, een enkele speler die een real time strategisch overzicht van het slagveld had.  Hij was verantwoordelijk voor het maken van bouwwerken en voor een strategie die het team moest verenigen.  Maar bij het ontwerp kwamen er aardig wat uitdagingen bij kijken.  Hoe ontwerpen we bijvoorbeeld de game zodat de commandant plezier kan hebben en zorgen we er tegelijkertijd voor dat de spelers in het veld er lol in hebben?  Hoe zorgen we ervoor dat de spelers en de commandant de waarde van elkaars bijdrage kunnen waarderen?  Hoe zorgen we ervoor dat de game nog steeds leuk is als je een vreselijke commandant hebt of, de omgekeerde situatie, als je een fantastische commandant bent met een vreselijk team?  We hebben maanden aan deze en andere problemen gewerkt en bereikten nooit een punt waarop we tevreden waren.  Bovendien was de game veel te ingewikkeld geworden omdat we probeerden een strategie-element in te bouwen dat voldoende diepgang bood om überhaupt een commandant toe te kunnen voegen.  Uiteindelijk hebben we de moeilijke beslissing genomen om hem uit de game te schrappen en verder te gaan."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment033.wav"   "[Robin Walker] We first showed TF2 at E3 in 1999, and here we are in 2007. So what took us so long?  The short answer is that it took us this long to make something we were happy with.  The long answer requires a look at our development process.  At its core is the assumption that we don't really know ahead of time what will be fun.  We know what has been fun in the past.  But if we've got 3 ideas on the table, we can't say for sure which one will be the most fun.  So, we've focused on developing a repeatable process that will find out.  It's based on a cycle of constant iteration, where evaluation is done by watching as many people play the game as possible.  In developing TF2, we tried out many, many features-a few of which made it to the final product, but most of which were cut.  For example, our initial versions of TF2 were focused on trying to build a game around the concept of a commander, a single player who had a real-time-strategy view of the battlefield.  He was responsible for building structures and providing a unifying strategy for the team.  But there were significant design challenges involved.  For instance, how do we design the game such that the commander can have fun, and at same time ensure that the players down on the ground can have fun?  How do we ensure that the players & the commander value the output of the other?  How do we ensure that the game is still fun if you have a terrible commander, or conversely, if you're a great commander with a terrible team?  We spent many months working on these and other issues, and never reached a point where we were satisfied.  In addition, our game had become overly complex, due to our attempts to add a strategy layer deep enough to warrant the addition of the commander in the first place.  In the end, we made the hard decision to remove him from the game and moved on."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment034.wav"   "[Kelly Thornton] Voltreffers vormen een van de kenmerken die zijn ontstaan uit onze aandacht voor snelheid. Het systeem van voltreffers probeert de hoogte- en dieptepunten van de game enigszins te beïnvloeden door de kans op een voltreffer te verhogen op basis van de recente prestaties van de speler. Kort gezegd: hoe beter je het doet, hoe groter de kans is dat je het goed blijft doen. Hiermee worden van die zeldzame hoogtepunten gecreëerd waarbij een enkele speler als een dolle tekeergaat en kort na elkaar 3 of 4 tegenstanders uitschakelt."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment034.wav"   "[Kelly Thornton] Critical hits are one of the features that resulted from our focus on pacing. The critical hit system attempts to slightly influence the highs and lows of the game, by increasing the chance of a critical hit based upon the player's recent performance. In summary, the better you're doing, the more likely you'll continue to do well. This helps create those rare high moments, where a single player goes on a rampage and gets 3 or 4 kills in rapid succession."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment035.wav"   "[Adrian Finol] Een van de belangrijkste veranderingen tussen Team Fortress Classic en Team Fortress 2 is dat de gegooide granaten zijn weggehaald. 
De meeste klassen konden een gewone handgranaat bij zich dragen, samen met een tweede granaat die meer bij de klasse paste.  Doordat Team Fortress 2 zich concentreerde op de unieke rollen van de klassen merkten we op dat de gewone handgranaat een krachtiger middel was om een gevecht te bepalen dan sommige primaire wapens.  Hierdoor gingen de klassen tijdens gevechten op elkaar lijken en dat was geen wenselijk effect.  Toen we een aantal patstellingen op de kaarten van Team Fortress Classic bekeken, zagen we bovendien dat die vaak het gevolg waren van het rondstrooien van granaten. Twee gevallen waren met name problematisch: het geval waarbij spelers herhaaldelijk granaten door ingangen gooien in de hoop vijanden te doden die daar zouden kunnen zitten, en het geval waarin spelers die op het punt staan dood te gaan al hun granaten in rap tempo achter elkaar gooien in de hoop na hun dood vijanden uit te schakelen.  Door de gewone handgranaten te schrappen, werd de game vrijwel meteen een stuk leuker, met name voor nieuwe spelers die vaak wat in de war waren over de manier waarop ze omkwamen wanneer een granaat voor hun voeten ontplofte. Toen we de granaten onderzochten die specifiek waren voor de klassen, kwamen we vergelijkbare problemen tegen.  Door ze uit de testgame weglieten, werden we nog meer gestimuleerd om de game leuker te maken.  Toen we eenmaal hadden besloten ze weg te halen, hebben we elke klasse geanalyseerd om te zien welke capaciteiten als gevolg van het besluit mogelijk verloren waren gegaan.  Aan sommige klassen hebben we andere capaciteiten toegevoegd als we het idee hadden dat ze niet meer in staat waren interessante beslissingen te nemen die verband hielden met het desbetreffende type granaat.
"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment035.wav"   "[Adrian Finol] One of the main changes between Team Fortress Classic and Team Fortress 2 was the removal of thrown grenades. 
Most classes could carry a standard hand grenade along with a secondary grenade, tied more closely to the class.  Team Fortress 2's focus on unique class roles led us to notice that the standard hand grenade was a more powerful combat decider than some of the primary weapons.  This made the classes more similar in combat-not a desired effect.  In addition, when we looked at some of Team Fortress Classic's map stalemates, they often resulted from large amounts of grenade spam. Two cases were particularly problematic:  That of players throwing grenades repeatedly through doorways, hoping to kill any enemies who might be there, and players on the verge of death throwing all their grenades in rapid succession, hoping to get a kill after they die.  Removing standard hand grenades made the game more fun almost immediately, especially for new players who were often confused as to why they died, when a grenade went off at their feet. When we examined the class-specific grenades, we found similar problems.  Eliminating them from playtests gave us yet another boost in making the game more fun.  Once we'd decided on removal, we analyzed each class to see what capabilities might have been lost as a result of the decision.  In some cases we added other capabilities, where we felt a class had lost the ability to make some interesting decisions, related to its special grenade type.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment036.wav"   "[Hamish McKenzie] Tegen het einde van het project, toen ander delen van de game al werden afgewerkt, bleken we nog wat tijd over te hebben voor extra animatie.  Er lagen verschillende ideeën op tafel, waaronder wapenspecifieke spotanimaties.  Bij het evalueren van kenmerken bekijken we met hoeveel andere kenmerken ze in verbinding staan, en bespottingen sprongen er duidelijk uit.  Ze zijn goed te gebruiken in combinatie met de killer freeze-cam, wat een extra dimensie toevoegt aan de relatie tussen de kwelgeest en zijn slachtoffer.  Ze boden ons een hele zichtbare plek om onze nieuwe technieken voor gezichtsanimatie te tonen die de speler van alle kanten kon bekijken. Ten slotte hebben de personages in TF2 enorm veel persoonlijkheid en waren bespottingen de perfecte manier om die persoonlijkheid middels animatie en stemacteren gestalte te geven."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment036.wav"   "[Hamish McKenzie] Late in the project, while other parts of the game were being finished up, we found ourselves with some time left over for extra animation.  There were several ideas on the table, including weapon-specific taunt animations.  When evaluating a feature, we look at how many other features it connects to, and taunts were the clear winner.  They play well with the killer freeze-cam, adding to the relationship between the nemesis and his victim.  They gave us a highly visible place to show off our new facial animation technology, allowing the player to examine it from all angles. Finally, TF2's characters have a lot of personality, and taunts were the perfect way to show that personality through animation and voice acting."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment037.wav"   "[Eric Smith] Voor Half-Life 2 hebben we iets ontwikkeld dat Response Rules heet, een systeem waarmee we de manier waarop personages dialoogregels uitspreken kunnen afstemmen op gebeurtenissen in de game die niet helemaal voorspelbaar zijn.  In Team Fortress 2 hebben de Response Rules voor het eerst uitgebreid naar een multiplayer-omgeving.  Bij het Response Rule-systeem worden spraakconcepten opgeslagen in een eenvoudig tekstbestand. De gamecode probeert de personages dan te laten spreken wanneer in de game wordt voldaan aan de regels en omstandigheden die in het tekstbestand worden gedefinieerd. Als een speler bijvoorbeeld zijn wapen herlaadt, krijgt het Response Rule-systeem een seintje dat het nu een goed moment is om een regel over herladen te zeggen. Het Response Rule-systeem controleert de status van de spelomgeving en vergelijkt die met een set regels waarmee wordt bepaald wat de beste dialoogregel bij dat spraakconcept is.  Als de speler nog maar weinig medkits heeft, kan hij iets anders zeggen dan wanneer hij helemaal fit is.  Hij kan een speciale regel uitspreken als hij de laatste 20 seconden meer dan twee vijanden heeft uitgeschakeld, weer andere regels als hij onderwater is, enzovoort.  Door dialogen en regels in scriptbestanden te zetten, kunnen de schrijvers van de game spraak aan de game toevoegen zonder dat ze ondersteuning voor de code nodig hebben.
"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment037.wav"   "[Eric Smith] For Half-Life 2 we developed something called Response Rules, a system that lets us fine-tune the way characters speak lines of dialog in response to game events that are not completely predictable.  In Team Fortress 2, we extended Response Rules to the multiplayer environment for the first time.  The Response Rule system works by listing speech concepts in a simple text file; the game code then makes characters attempt to speak when the rules or conditions defined in the text file are met in the game. For instance, when a player reloads his weapon, this signals the Response Rule system that now would be an appropriate time to speak a line about reloading. The Response Rule system checks the state of the world, and matches it to a set of rules that determine the best line of dialog to use for that speech concept.  If the player's health is low, he may speak a different reloading line than if he is completely healthy.  He could play a special line if he has killed more than two enemies in the last 20 seconds, another set of lines if he's underwater, and so on.  Keeping dialog and rules in script files gives the game's writers the ability to add speech to the game without needing any code support.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment038.wav"   "[Moby Francke] Bij onze eerdere besprekingen over weergavestijlen voor de personages besloten we dat we een illustratieve of gestileerde weergave wilden zonder tot het uiterste te gaan zoals sommige toon shaders. We wilden zachtere lijnen voor schaduwen dan kenmerkend was voor dit soort weergave.  We gebruikten dus een 2D-textuur om de lichtval op de personages aan te geven, en op de punten waar licht en donker elkaar raken, hebben we een vleugje warmte toegevoegd om bij de overgang een kleurexplosie te laten ontstaan. Toen we eenmaal het juiste schaduwmodel hadden bereikt, voegden we aan de personages een rand toe zodat ze een mooie highlight langs de randen van hun silhouet kregen waardoor ze duidelijk zichtbaar zijn in hun 3D-omgeving."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment038.wav"   "[Moby Francke] In our early discussions of rendering styles for the characters, we decided we wanted them to have a look that was illustrative or stylized, without going to the extremes of most toon shaders. We wanted softer lines for shading than was typical for this sort of rendering.  So, we used a 2-D texture to define the lighting on the characters, and at the point where light and dark meet, we added a hint of warmth to give it that burst of color at the transition. Once we had achieved the right shading model, we added a rim-term to the characters, so they would have a nice highlight around the edges of their silhouettes, which helps them to stand out from the surrounding 3d world."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment039.wav"   "[Dhabih Eng] De uitdaging van het deeltjessysteem was het creëren van effecten die leuk en spannend om te zien waren, zonder dat ze zo overdreven waren dat niemand de betekenis ervan in de game begreep.  Bij een doorsnee-gevecht worden er zoveel effecten tegelijk op het scherm weergegeven dat het gevaar bestaat dat het er uit gaat zien als een rommeltje.  De effecten werden daarom verfijnd zodat ze scherper en eenvoudiger werden.  De effecten die het belangrijkste waren voor de gameplay maakten we gemakkelijker te zien en de effecten die voornamelijk mooi waren om te zien lieten we wat meer opgaan in de achtergrond.  "
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment039.wav"   "[Dhabih Eng] The challenge of the particle system was to create effects that were fun and visually exciting, without being so 'over the top' that no one could read their meaning in the game.  In a typical match, there are so many effects onscreen at the same time, that the biggest danger is visual clutter.  Therefore, the effects were refined to be cleaner and simpler.  Those that were most important for gameplay were made easier to see, while those that were mainly eye-candy were allowed to fall into the background.  "
"#commentary\tf2-Comment040.wav"   "[Robin Walker] Met negen klassen personages en minstens zoveel wapens en unieke capaciteiten was een van onze grootste uitdagingen het weergeven van al deze combinaties aan de spelers zonder ze ermee te overstelpen.  Zelfs de shortlist met essentiële gegevens is al indrukwekkend, bijvoorbeeld de doelen op de kaart, waar vrienden zich bevinden, wie hen beschiet en met welk wapen, enzovoort.  We konden deze gegevens niet allemaal visualiseren, dus moesten we eerst een prioriteitenlijst maken met de dingen die elke speler moest weten om gewoon plezier te kunnen hebben.  Informatie die ze konden opdoen door gewoon het spel te spelen, zoals bijvoorbeeld de indeling van de kaart, was van secundair belang. Er was echter ook informatie, zoals de onkwetsbaarheidslading van de Medic, die volledig onzichtbaar zou zijn tenzij we die bekendmaken.  We hebben geprobeerd het koppelen van 2D-elementen aan de HUD zoveel mogelijk te vermijden omdat we spelers wilden laten kijken naar de 3D-wereld die we hebben gebouwd in plaats van een of andere abstracte voorstelling.  Spelers zien bijvoorbeeld de Spy´s van hun eigen team altijd als Spy, maar ze moeten weten hoe deze is vermomd voor het andere team.  We probeerden snel iets uit door een pictogram voor de huidige vermomming van de Spy boven diens hoofd te laten zweven.  Het pictogram bleek de testspelers in de war te brengen.   Toen we het probleem aanpakten door de Spy uit te dossen met uitgeknipte papieren maskers, bleek dat niet alleen te passen bij de humoristische stijl van de game, maar bleken de spelers ook direct over alle relevante informatie te beschikken door een snelle blik op het model van de Spy, zodat ze zich konden blijven concentreren op de personages en de actie van de game.  We zagen dit als een goede les. Door vast te houden aan een sterk ontwerpprincipe worden we vaak gedwongen om betere oplossingen aan te dragen dan wanneer we de makkelijke weg zouden kiezen."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment040.wav"   "[Robin Walker] With nine classes of characters, and so many weapons and unique abilities, one of our biggest challenges was exposing all these combinations to players without overwhelming them.  Even the shortlist of essential information is intimidating, including map goals, the whereabouts of their friends, who's shooting them with what weapon, and so on.  We didn't have any way to make all of this information visual, so first we had to prioritize and come up with an essential list of things every player needed to know in order to just have fun.  Information they could learn by playing the game-such as map layout-was of secondary importance; but there was also information, such as the Medic's invulnerability charge, that would be completely invisible unless we exposed it.  We tried to avoid attaching 2D elements to the HUD as much as possible, since we wanted players to be looking at the 3D world we'd built rather than some abstract representation.  For example, players always see their own team's spies as a spy, but they need to know how the spy is disguised to the other team.  We tried a quick hack where we put an icon representing the spy's current disguise floating above his head.  The icon proved baffling to playtesters.   When we tackled the problem by putting cut-out paper masks on the spy, it not only fit the humorous style of the game, but it let players get all pertinent information directly from a quick look at the spy's model, thus keeping them focused on the characters and on the action of the game.  We took this as a lesson, in how holding ourselves to a strong design principle can often force us to come up with better solutions, than if we'd taken the easy route."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment041.wav"   "[Jason Mitchell] soldier up to here: setpos 281,531250 3295,468750 -124,027405;setang 4,553997 176,268036 0,000000 Om te komen tot een bepaalde schaduwstijl voor personages die klopt met de reclametekeningen uit het begin van de twintigste eeuw die onze ontwerpen hebben beïnvloed, veranderen we het strooilicht op de personages. Hier zien we de Soldier zoals hij verschijnt in Team Fortress 2 met onze illustratieve schaduwstijl. Let op de scherpe overgang tussen de lichte en donkere kanten van de Soldier wanneer hij wordt aangelicht door het licht in de volgende ruimte. Met traditionele belichting [r_identitylightwarp instellen op 1] zoals je hier kunt zien, worden de personages te zacht aangelicht, wat niet past bij de illustratieve stijl. Met het illustratieve belichtingsmodel [r_identitylightwarp instellen op 0] worden de personages aangelicht op een manier die beter aansluit bij de totale ontwerpstijl.  back soldier up to here (dark corner near above position): setpos 482,125000 3267,843750 -124,027405;setang -1,386003 -137,399948 0,000000 Een ander facet van de illustratieve schaduw is het gebruik van randbelichting om de silhouetten van personages te accentueren om te voorkomen dat ze opgaan in hun omgeving. Zonder de randbelichting [r_rimlight instellen op 0] gaan de personages op in de achtergrond. Met de randbelichting [r_rimlight instellen op 1] zijn de personages zichtbaar tegen de rest van de omgeving en passen ze beter bij de ontwerpstijl van Team Fortress 2."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment041.wav"   "[Jason Mitchell] soldier up to here: setpos 281.531250 3295.468750 -124.027405;setang 4.553997 176.268036 0.000000 To achieve a style of character shading which is consistent with the early 20th Century commercial illustrations that influenced our art direction, we alter the diffuse lighting on characters. Here, we can see the Soldier as he appears in Team Fortress 2, using our illustrative shading style. Note the tight transition between the light and dark sides of the Soldier as he is lit by the light in the next room. Using traditional lighting [set r_identitylightwarp to 1] as seen here, the character lighting appears too soft and does not fit our illustrative style. With the illustrative lighting model [set r_identitylightwarp to 0], our characters are lit in a way which better fits our overall art style.  back soldier up to here (dark corner near above position): setpos 482.125000 3267.843750 -124.027405;setang -1.386003 -137.399948 0.000000 Another facet of illustrative shading is the use of rim highlights to accentuate the silhouettes of characters to keep them from blending into the scenery. Without the rim lighting [set r_rimlight to 0], the character blends into the background. With the rimlighting, [set r_rimlight to 1] characters are visible against the rest of the scene and better fit the art style of Team Fortress 2."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment042.wav"   "[Alden Kroll] Tweedimensionale HUD-elementen zorgen voor een bepaald ontwerpprobleem omdat ze er goed en duidelijk uit moeten zien, ongeacht de resolutie waarbij de gebruiker de game speelt. Omdat breedbeeldschermen met hoge resolutie tegenwoordig zo algemeen verkrijgbaar zijn, kan dat veel geheugen en een hoop werk kosten om in te spelen op de verschillende schermresoluties. Het probleem voor TF2 was een nog grotere uitdaging omdat we in onze HUD veel gladde, gebogen elementen wilden gebruiken. We ontwikkelden een nieuw schaduwsysteem voor het maken van lijntekeningen.  Met het systeem kunnen we beelden maken met een vaste resolutie waarbij gelijkmatige silhouetten worden gemaakt, zelfs wanneer deze worden vergroot naar een zeer hoge resolutie. Met dit schaduwsysteem kunnen ook contouren en buitenschaduwen worden gemaakt, en kan in de 3D-ruimte worden toegepast op omgevingselementen als borden.  "
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment042.wav"   "[Alden Kroll] Two-dimensional HUD elements present a particular art problem, because they have to look good and sharp no matter what resolution the user is running their game at. Given today's availability of high resolution wide-screen displays, this can require a lot of texture memory and a lot of work anticipating different display resolutions. The problem for TF2 was even more daunting because of our desire to include a lot of smooth curved elements in our HUD. We developed a new shader system for drawing 'line art' images.  The system allows us to create images at a fixed resolution that produced smooth silhouettes even when scaled up to a very high resolution. This shader system also handles outlining and drop-shadows, and can be applied in the 3D space to world elements such as signs.  "
"#commentary\tf2-Comment043.wav"   "[Chris Green] We wilden in Team Fortress 2 veel speciale deeltjeseffecten laten terugkomen om verschillende wapens en capaciteiten van klassen te benadrukken. In vorige versies van de Source-engine moesten de programmeurs voor alle deeltjeseffecten aangepaste code schrijven. Voor Team Fortress 2 hebben we een systeem gemaakt waarmee ontwerpers zonder de hulp van een programmeur nieuwe deeltjessystemen snel konden creëren en bestaande herhaaldelijk konden verfijnen. Met een bewerkingsfunctie in de game kunnen ontwerpers de definities van deeltjessystemen bewerken en de effecten ervan in de game direct bekijken.  De bewerkingsfunctie biedt tekenaars de mogelijkheid om ´bouwstenen´ van modulaire effecten aan elkaar te koppelen om ingewikkelde visuele effecten te creëren. Wat het deeltjessysteem zelf betreft, hebben we een groot deel van de systeemberekeningen overgebracht naar de grafische versneller, waardoor we het aantal deeltjes op het scherm kunnen vergroten zonder de rasterfrequentie te verlagen."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment043.wav"   "[Chris Green] We intended Team Fortress 2 to feature many special particle effects to enhance the wide variety of weapons and class abilities. In previous versions of the Source engine, all particle effects required that custom code be written by the programmers. For Team Fortress 2, we created a system where designers can rapidly create new particle systems and iteratively refine existing ones, without programmer involvement. An in-game editor allows designers to edit the definitions of particle systems and immediately preview effects in the game itself.  The editor also allows artists to connect modular effect 'building blocks' to create complex visual effects. As for the particle system itself, we have offloaded many of the system calculations to the graphics accelerator, which allows us to increase the number of particles onscreen without reducing the framerate."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment044.wav"   "[Eric Kirchmer] Toen we de vormgeving van onze wereld en de personages eenmaal onder de knie hadden, konden we ons concentreren op de wapens en andere gadgets. Hoewel deze dingen hun oorsprong in de realiteit hebben, wijken ze vaak aanzienlijk af. De raketlanceerder van de Soldier klopt met het algemene beeld van een op de schouder gedragen raketlanceerder, maar heeft op de een of andere manier vier raketten in een magazijn. Om dit te rechtvaardigen en het idee van de gestileerde Spy-technologie te benadrukken, hebben we de wapens zodanig ontworpen dat ze er uit zien als aangepast geschut dat door elk personage voor eigen doeleinden is gepersonaliseerd en bewerkt. In overeenstemming met de industriële stijl van de game, hebben we voor de primaire wapens gekeken naar de principes voor productontwerp uit de jaren '60, en richtten we ons vervolgens op muziekinstrumenten voor de secundaire en andere wapens met het idee dat deze de connectie tussen de secundaire items en de persoonlijkheden van de personages zouden versterken."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment044.wav"   "[Eric Kirchmer] Once we had a handle on the art direction for our world and characters, we turned our attention to the weapons and gadgets. While these objects have some grounding in reality, they usually diverge in significant ways. For instance, the soldier's rocket launcher fits the general mold of a shoulder mounted rocket launcher, but somehow manages to hold four rockets in a clip. To justify this, and play up our stylized Spy-tech fiction, we designed the weapons to look like customized pieces of hardware, personalized and modified by each character to suit his own ends. In keeping with the industrial theme of the game, we looked to 60's era product design principles for the primary weapons, then focused on musical instruments for secondary and melee weapons, thinking these would reinforce the connection between the secondary items and each character's personality."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment045.wav"   "[Jim Hughes] Bij het ontwerpen van gebieden voor grote gevechten proberen we ingewikkeldheid en chaos te vermijden.  Ingewikkelde geometrie brengt spelers in de war waardoor ze vijanden moeilijk kunnen opsporen en waardoor ze worden belemmerd in hun normale bewegingen en het richten tijdens gevechten. De meest chaotische gevechten ontstaan wanneer de ruimte niet groot genoeg is voor het aantal spelers dat erin vecht.  In dit laatste gedeelte van de kaart wilden we gedurende een bepaalde tijd een vrij gevecht laten woeden voordat iemand de uiteindelijke overwinning zou kunnen behalen.  Om dit te bereiken, hebben we een grote open ruimte met diverse ingangen gebouwd en spelers op verscheidene hoogten verschillende aanvals- en verdedigingsopties gegeven. In plaats van te vertrouwen op liften en ladders, vertrouwden we op hellingen omdat deze altijd bewegingsvrijheid geven en de spelers niet insluiten.  Door het testspelen hebben we veel veranderingen doorgevoerd in de afmetingen van de ruimte, de grootte van de elementen die dekking bieden en de grootte van de ingangen, zodat we zeker wisten dat de ruimte groot genoeg zou zijn voor een gevecht met vele spelers.  "
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment045.wav"   "[Jim Hughes] When designing areas for high levels of combat, we try to avoid complexity and chaos.  Complex geometry confuses players, making it hard for them to track enemies, and interfering with their movement and aiming during combat. The most chaotic combat tends to occur when the size of the room fails to support the number of players fighting in it.  In this final area of the map, we wanted a freeform battle to rage for some time before anyone could achieve a decisive victory.  To achieve this, we built a wide open area with several entrances, and gave players a variety of attack and defense options at various heights. Rather than depend on elevators and ladders, we relied on ramps, since these allow freedom of movement at all times instead of confining players.  Through playtesting we made many changes to the dimensions of the room, the size of cover elements, and the size of the entrances, thus ensuring the area could accommodate a battle of many players.  "
"#commentary\tf2-Comment046.wav"   "[Aaron Barber] In tegenstelling tot kaarten in TF zoals 2fort en Well, waarop je een oprukkende blauwe of rode kant hebt, kunnen de vier hoofdarena's van Hydro door een van beide teams worden ingenomen. We hadden een algemeen thema nodig waarin bouwsels zoals rotswanden en tunnels gerechtvaardigd waren, maar dat ook een neutrale kleurstelling had. We hebben gekozen voor een woestijnthema met een kleurschema van roodbruine steen, een frisblauwe lucht en neutrale lichtkleuren die de omgeving aanvullen. De kleuren van de afzonderlijke gebieden variëren enigszins maar passen nog steeds bij elkaar.
"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment046.wav"   "[Aaron Barber] Unlike maps in TF such as 2fort and Well, which have progressively blue and red sides, Hydro's four main arenas can be owned by one team or the other. We needed an overall theme that justified structures like rock walls and tunnels, but which also had a neutral color scheme. We chose a desert theme with a palette of reddish-brown rock, cool blue sky and neutral light colors that complement the surrounding area. The colors of the seperate areas vary slightly but still key together.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment047.wav"   "[Chet Faliszek] De verteller van Team Fortress 2, Ellen McLain, is de enige stemacteur in alle producten in de Orange Box.  Voor haar rol in Team Fortress 2 hebben we Ellen de regels op meerdere manieren laten inspreken, waarbij ze behoorlijk vrij was in het invullen van de persoonlijkheden.  De vijfde poging was raak. De teleurgestelde en lichtelijk geïrriteerde, duivelse overlord maakt duidelijk dat in Team Fortress een gelijkspel niet wil zeggen dat iedereen heeft gewonnen, maar dat iedereen heeft verloren."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment047.wav"   "[Chet Faliszek] The announcer for Team Fortress 2, Ellen McLain, has the rare distinction of being the only voice actor to perform in all the products in the Orange box.  For her role in Team Fortress 2, we had Ellen try various reads on the same lines letting her ad-lib different personalities.  On the 5th try, she came up with the winner. Her disappointed and slightly angry evil overlord clearly lets you know, in the world of Team Fortress a tie does not mean everyone wins, but that everyone loses."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment048.wav"   "[Laura Dubuk] Dit gebied stelde ons voor een moeilijk probleem. Omdat het strijdperk voornamelijk een interieur is, konden we niet veel doen om de basisstructuur te veranderen. We concentreerden ons dus op de zorgvuldige vormgeving van het interieur om een beeldende ruimte te creëren. Het gebouw was in feite een doos met grote, rechthoekige ramen, gecontrasteerd door ronde elementen (generatoren) in het midden. Voor de nodige diepte en perspectief hebben we lineaire elementen zoals balustrades en kabels toegevoegd. Op de vloer gebruikten we contrasterende donker- en lichtwaarden met gangen die een interessant patroon vormden. Al deze elementen zorgen er samen voor dat de aandacht van de speler wordt getrokken door de vlag, die altijd het middelpunt van de arena moet zijn."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment048.wav"   "[Laura Dubuk] This area presented a difficult problem. Since the arena is primarily an interior, there wasn't much we could do to alter its basic structure, so we concentrated on careful management of the interior shapes to create an iconic space. The building is essentially a box with big rectangular windows, contrasted by round elements (generators) in the center. To create depth and parallax, we added linear elements such as railings and cables. We used contrasting values of dark and light on the floor, with walkways to create an interesting value pattern. All these elements work together to draw the player's eye to the flag--which must always be the focal point of the arena."
}
}
